Guide to the Records of the Puerto Rico Project 1943-1951 (Bulk 1947-1949) RG 3
New York University Libraries, Publisher
Records of the Puerto Rico Study 1943-1951, (Bulk 1948-1949)
RG 3
Approximately 4.0 linear feet (7 AB including 1 oversized box)
Research Institute for the Study of Man/New York University Archives
Steward, Julian H.
The Puerto Rico Project was a comprehensive study conducted by Dr. Julian H. Steward and a select team of anthropologists between 1947 and 1949. The collection includes correspondence, minutes, interviews, reports, journal accounts, fieldwork reports, printed matter, manuscripts, thesis, maps, and ephemera.
Provenance
TThe Records of the Puerto Rico Project were generated by a team of professional anthropologists under the direction of Dr. Julian H. Steward, chair of the anthropology department at Columbia University. Dr. Steward and other members of the team were professional associates of Dr. Vera D. Rubin, founder and direction of the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM) and may have transferred the collection to RISM headquarters.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Puerto Rico Project was an in-depth study of the Island's population organized by Dr. Jaime Benitez, chancellor of the University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras Campus, with the assistance of Clarence Senior, director of the University's Center of Social Science Investigations. In early 1947, the proposed study was brought to the attention of Dr. Julian Steward (1902 - 1972), chair of Columbia University's Anthropology Department.
By December 1947, the organization of Project goals, research hypotheses and methodology were underway. The fieldwork phase of the Project began in February 1948, coinciding with Operation Bootstrap ("Operación Manos a la Obra"), the Puerto Rico government's ambitious plan to industrialize the Island. Dr. Steward chose many of his graduate students to head fieldwork investigations. This core group included noted leaders in the field of anthropology: Sidney Mintz, Eric R. Wolf, Elena Padilla Seda, Robert A. Manners, John Murra, Raymond Scheele and others. Students from the Universities of Puerto Rico and Chicago also assisted in the study to gain professional training.
In contrast to previous anthropological studies that investigated communities as isolated units, the Puerto Rico Project not only assessed the impact of industrialization among rural communities, it produced an analysis of the relationship between those communities and the Island through oral history, labor studies, and comparative surveys of sociocultural patterns.
Fieldwork activities concluded in August 1949, followed by a year of supplemental library research. A preliminary report was published in 1951. Funding from the University of Puerto Rico, the Rockefeller Foundation, the Wenner-Gren Foundation, and the Research Board of the University of Illinois helped to facilitate completion of the final report, published as The People of Puerto Rico: A Study in Social Anthropology.
Sources:
Shimkin, Demetri B. "Julian H. Steward: A Contributor to Fact and Theory in Cultural Anthropology," Process and Patterns in Culture: Essays in Honor of Julian H. Steward Essays in Honor of Julian H. Steward. Robert A. Manners, ed.
Steward, Julian H., et al, eds. Preface. The People of Puerto Rico: A Study in Social Anthropology. A Social Science Research Center Study, College of Social Sciences, University of Puerto Rico, University of Illinois Press, 1956 (retained by RISM).
Material from the collection was also used in the finding aid.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Puerto Rico Project comprise 4.0 linear feet (7 AB including 1 oversize box) and span the years 1943 - 1951. The bulk of the records, generated between 1947 and 1949, represent a unique, cooperative effort in modern anthropology. The collection includes bilingual correspondence, conference papers, minutes, interviews, journal entries, fieldwork reports, manuscripts, clippings, printed matter, miscellaneous papers, and maps. The papers have been arranged as follows: Series I. Correspondence, Series II. Minutes, Series III. Interviews, Series IV. Journal entries, Series V. Project Reports, Series VI. Draft Manuscript Papers, Series VII. Miscellaneous Papers, Series VIII. Maps. Descriptive details are included in the scope and content note for each series.
Although the collection represents a small portion of a comprehensive study, the records provide critical insight into the impact of industrialization on the Island's cultural history, demography, land use patterns, economics, race relations, migration, and family kinship structure. The records also highlight the influence of external economic and political forces.
Although critical gaps occur between Nov - Jun 1948, Jun 1949 - 1950, and during the final phase of the Project, Series I. Correspondence, details the Project's development and highlights the relationships of the fieldwork team. Series II. Conference Papers provides insight into the research structure of the Project with particular emphasis on the development of hypotheses and fieldwork methodology. Although there is some overlap between Series III. Interviews and Series IV. Journals, the records in both series detail day-to-day life in Puerto Rico during the transitional period. Series V. Project Reports consists of field data submitted by and circulated among members of the fieldwork team. These reports helped shape and guide the research methodology.
Although Series VI. Draft Manuscript Papers is incomplete, it sheds light on the way in which the final report was organized. Series VII Miscellaneous Papers, includes notes, political flyers, brochures and some photographs. A unique set of local and regional maps of Puerto Rico, published prior to the Project, comprise Series VIII.
Two items, formerly housed in RISM's Library for Caribbean Research (LCR), have been appended to the collection. Report on the Selection of a Community for Anthropological Study, a thesis written by Irene Caro, documents fieldwork in Puerto Rico and contains a valuable glossary of common terms in the Spanish language. The second document, Canamelar: The Subculture of a Rural Sugar Plantation Proletariat, written by Sidney Mintz, appears to be a chapter of a larger, unidentified manuscript.
Arrangement
The Puerto Rico Study Collection has been organized chronologically and arranged into the following series:
I. Correspondence
II. Minutes
III. Interviews
IV. Journal Entries
V. Project Reports
VI. Draft Manuscript Papers
VII. Miscellaneous Papers
VIII. Maps
Access Points
Subject Names:
Armstrong, Robert G., 1917-; Manners, Robert A. (Robert Alan), 1913-; Muñoz Marín, Luis, 1898-; Mintz, Sidney Wilfred, 1922-; Murra, John V. 1916-; Padilla, Elena, 1923-; Steward, Julian Haynes, 1902-1972.; Wolf, Eric R., 1923-
Subject Organizations:
Columbia University--Faculty.; Partido Popular Democrático (P.R.).; University of Puerto Rico (Rio Piedras Campus).
Subject Topics:
Puerto Rico--Social Life and customs.; Puerto Rico--Economic conditions.; Economic development--Puerto Rico.; Puerto Rico--social conditions.
Subject Places:
Puerto Rico.; New York.
Document Types:
Clippings.; Correspondence.; Interviews.; Journals.; Manuscripts.; Maps.; Minutes.; Photographs.; Printed matter.; Thesis.
Related Material at the NYU Archives
The Vera D. Rubin Papers
Separated Material
No materials have been removed from the collection.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Series I: Correspondence, April 1948 - August 1950, n.d.
  7 folders, arranged chronologically. This series consists of incoming and outgoing letters between fieldworkers in Puerto Rico and field director John Murra in New York.
  - Correspondence, Apr 1948-Jun 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Aug 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Sep 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Oct 1948-Nov 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Jun 1949-Aug 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, labor statistics, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II: Minutes, December 1947 - January 1949
  9 folders, arranged chronologically. This series mainly consists of minutes generated during Project conferences and meetings. The papers, which highlight planning details and methodology of fieldwork investigation, include agendas, minutes, research categories, work plans and notes. Several reports, referenced in the minutes are also included.
  - Typescript minutes, notes, ephemera, Dec 1947-Feb 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Proposed conference agenda, research categories, May 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, reports, May 1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, community studies form, notes, May 1948; , undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Notes (handwritten), May 1948; , undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Typescript minutes, May 1948-Jun 1948; , undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Typescript minutes, notes, Jun 1948-Jul 1948; , undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Typescript and handwritten minutes, Jul 1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Project meeting work plan, class taxonomy by community, comparative community data, Jan 1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series III: Interviews, August - October 1948, n.d.
  5 folders, arranged chronologically. This series consists of typescript field interviews conducted by Sidney Mintz and Charles Rosario, a student at the University of Puerto Rico. Coded to conform the Project hypotheses, the interviews address issues of land reform, labor patterns, race relations, religion, and culture.
  - Instructions for use of questionnaire, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Interviews, Aug 1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Interviews, Sep 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Interviews, Oct 1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Interview questionnaires (blank), undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Journal Entries, January 1948 - April [1949?]
  approximately .5 linear feet (1 AB), arranged chronologically. This series is comprised of bilingual, typescript accounts of field observations that were originally maintained as a journal. Although most of the entries appear to have been submitted by Sidney Mintz and Charles Rosario, the bracketed question marks represent unauthored entries. A small journal kept by Elena Padilla Seda is also included.
  - Unsigned Entry [S. Mintz?], Jan 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Descriptive and historic notes related to interviews, entries S. Mintz, Aug 1948-Sep 1948; , undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Entries, S. Mintz, Oct 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Entries, S. Mintz, Oct 1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Entries, S. Mintz, Oct 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Entries, C. Rosario, Oct 1948-Nov 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Entries, S. Mintz, Nov 1948 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Entries, S. Mintz, Nov 1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Entries, S. Mintz, Dec 1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Entries, C. Rosario [?], Dec 1948 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Entries, S. Mintz, Jan 1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Entries, C. Rosario [?], Jan 1949 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Entries, C. Rosario [?], Jan 1949 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Entries, C. Rosario [?]; small, partially used journal containing notes and drawings by Elena Padilla Seda, Feb 1948-Aug 1949 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Entries C. Rosario [?], April [1949?] (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Series V: Project Reports, 1946 - April 1950, n.d.
  1.0 linear feet (2 AB) arranged chronologically. This series features a number of typescript reports which have been organized as two subseries. Subseries a. Research Methodology details the development of research hypotheses. Subseries b. Field Research consists of statistical data, community studies and reference maps used in the study. Report titles appear in italics.
  - Subseries a. Research Methodology
    - Correspondence, master lists of hypotheses, May 1948-Jun 1948; , undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Criteria of Organization and Integration, Robert Armstrong, Third Sugar Community- Problem of Selection, Summary of Comparative Data, May 1948; , undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - untitled report regarding research categories; Quantitative data for localities [John Murra?], Nov 1948; , undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Subseries b. Field Research
    - Statistical data; Programa De Trabajo [soil conservation map transferred to Series VIII, Oversized materials], Plan De Trabajo from Distrito De Conservacion De Suelos Oeste, Nov 1946-Nov 1947; , undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Reports on local crops, land use, labor, population, and working conditions organized by research category, Jan 1948; , undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Reports on Palmas Altas [one incomplete]; children's artwork and writings; notes, Jan 1948-May 1949; , undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Information Relative to Selection of Urban Industrial Community, statistical data, printed matter, notes, Apr 1948-May 1948; , undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Conversation with F. Romero Salvatore Consentino, National Labor Review Board (NLRB), and David Sachs, May 1948 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - PIP Meeting at Quebradillas, notes, Jun 1948; , undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Special report on race, submitted by S. Mintz and C. Rosario, Aug 1948 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Bi-weekly reports submitted by Eric Wolf, Angelina Saavedra de Rosa, Robert Manners and others, Aug 1948-Dec 1948; , undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Some Thinking on National Culture, Eric Wolf; Puerto Rico and a National Culture, Bob Manners; National Character, Sidney Mintz and Charles Rosario, Sep 1948; , undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Costo de Cosecho por Tonelada Marzo 1946 - Zafra 1946, Dec 1948 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Reports on marketing, export crops, standard of living, economics, communications organized by research category, Jan 1948-Feb 1949; , undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Draft theses, notes, Mar 1948-Apr 1950 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Concepts and Problems Under-lying Field Research [author unknown], undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Information Relative to Urban and Industrial Communities in Puerto Rico, Beatrice M. Howell, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Survey Report: Santa Isabel, S. Mintz, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Some Temporary Thinking on National Culture as an Area Problem [author unknown], undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Details to be Observed [relates to children], Kay Wolf, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - San Jose: A Coffee Growing Community, A Thumbnail Sketch, Eric Wolf, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Azucar y Poblacion, [Sidney Mintz?], undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Aspects and Interpretations of the Development and Function of Religion in Puerto Rico [author unknown], undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Aspects and Interpretations of the Development and Functioning of the Family In Puerto Rico [author unknown], undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Descripcion Geografica Del Municipo De Caguas, Ramon Gandfa Cordova; handwritten notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Puerto Rico - Government and Politics, Fifty years of American Rule [author unknown], undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Summary of Hist. Politica Soc. De P.R. [author unknown], undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Research notes: Puerto Rico's government and political party system, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Research citations, The U.S. and P.R., Trial by Jury, The Civil Service system, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Research citations, The Study of Society, draft notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - The Local Upper Class [author unknown], draft notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Discussion of Characteristics, Barrio Pozas [author unknown]; miscellaneous, incomplete reports, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series VI: Draft Manuscript Papers, 1948 - 1950, n.d.
  Approximately .75 linear feet (1 AB, four folders), arranged chronologically. This series consists of a draft manuscript, that may represent efforts to organize the final report. Sequentially numbered and coded to conform to the Project hypotheses (see Series V. Project Reports, subseries a. Research Methodology), the manuscript is a compilation of journal entries, interviews and community studies. The following sections are missing: pp. 124 - 235, 236 - 304, 563 - 734, and 1412 - 1571.
  - Introductory material, drafts, graph chart, notes [Julian H. Steward], 1948-1949[?] (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript pp. 447 - 476, Oct 1948 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript pp. 477 - 493, draft notes, ephemera, Oct 1948 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript pp. 494 - 527, Oct 1948 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Manuscript pp. 528 - 562, Oct 1948 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - [Note: Fieldwork in Norcora], genealogical chart, Manuscript pp. 946-1006, note, Jan 1949 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Manuscript pp. 1007-1063, Jan 1949 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Manuscript pp. 1064 - 1100, Feb 1949 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript pp. 1101 - 1162, Feb 1949 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript pp. 1288 - 1367, Apr 1949 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Memo from JHS [Julian H. Steward] manuscript outline, Jul 1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series VII: Miscellaneous Papers, Dec 1943; 1947 - Feb 1949, n.d.
  .5 linear feet (1 AB). Arranged chronologically. This series contains varied materials, including printed matter, theatre advertisements, a photograph contact sheet and ephemera. Items of special interest include a form letter signed by former Puerto Rico governor Luis Munoz and political flyers.
  - Form letter signed by former Governor Luis Munoz Marin, Dec. 1943 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Anthropology-Sociology class calendar; outline, bibliography; essay on folk society, notes, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Programs for Teatro Taboas and Teatro Boringuen in Manati, Puerto Rico, Jun 1948-Jul 1948 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Political flyers for Partido Independista Puertorriqueno in Cauguas, Puerto Rico; related voting material, Sep 1948; , undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Brochures and print material detailing cooperative credit unions in Puerto Rico, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Photo contact sheet of children in urban setting, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Series VIII: Maps, Mar 1944 - May 1946, n.d.
  1.0 linear feet (2 folders, 1 oversized box), arranged according to size. The oversized material in this series includes government, regional and land use maps of Puerto Rico. Hand drawn maps of local communities are also included.
  - Municipio Del Hormigueros, topographical map prepared by the Dept. of Interior, May 1946 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Junta de Planificacion de Puerto Rico; hand drawn map of the General Configuration of the Agrarian Reform Society, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Oeste SC District Map, U.S. Dept. of Conservation Service, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Municipo De Camuy, U.S. Geological Survey and the Dept. of the Interior, May 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Hand drawn map of sugar cane farms, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Hand drawn map of Ciales, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Censo de Transito [Traffic Map] of Puerto Rico, Dept. of the Interior, Mar 1944 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Geographical survey maps of Florida and Ciales, Puerto Rico, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Land Use Map of Puerto Rico Puerto Rico Planning Board, Jun 1944 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Appendix
  Two additional monographs, a thesis and manuscript, formerly housed in the Library for Caribbean Research (LCR) at the Research Institute for the Study of Man, have been appended to the collection. These items provide document the fieldwork phase of the Project.
  - Report on the Selection of a Community for Anthropological Study, by Isabel S. Caro, Dec 1951 (Box 7, Item 1)
  - Canamelar: The Subculture of a Rural Sugar Plantation Proletariat, by Sidney Mintz, undated (Box 7, Item 2)